buy the dip and you're going to regret
buying the dip. I think sharp is
useless.
>> Let me extend that conversation to this
whole idea of active versus passive.
>> I take it with a grain of salt. Trading
is nothing more than solving your own
financial problems. And uh my financial
problems are different than other
people's. Stay in the now. Don't predict
and understand yourself.
[music]
Tom, thank you so much for taking time
to talk to us. You've been one of the
most quietly influential voices in the
trading world. Someone whose calm,
disciplined approach has inspired
generations of systematic traders. For
those of you who may not know Tom, he is
called Mr. Serenity, a name Jack
Schwagger gave him in the book The New
Market Wizards. He began his career as a
chemical engineer, but what really set
him apart was how he brought in an
engineer's precision and process
thinking into trading. In the early
1980s, he founded Trendstat Capital
Management, one of the pioneering
systematic trend following firms in the
US, managing nearly $600 million at its
peak. Trendstat was about building
systems that could think, act, and
manage risk without emotions. Tom
designed processes that turned market
data into orders. A true engineers
version of trading. He was among the
first to emphasize position sizing,
volatility control, and diversification
long before those ideas became
mainstream in portfolio management. But
perhaps more than his technical mastery,
it's his philosophy that continues to
resonate with many. Tom believes the
real edge in trading comes not from
indicators or predictions but from
mastering oneself. Our emotions, our
processes, and our patience. His motto,
enjoy the ride, perfectly sums it up.
Markets rise and fall, systems win and
lose. The goal is to stay balanced and
keep learning. Even after retiring from
Trendstat in 2003, Tom continues to
trade and mentor design systems that can
be managed in under an hour a day
because he believes good trading should
give you more life, not take it away.
Tom, it's a real honor to have you with
us today. You influence many of us think
about systems, risk, and the art of
staying calm in chaos. Let me start with
something simple. When people call you
Mr. Serenity, what does that mean to
you? And has that calmness always come
to you naturally or did trading teach it
to you?
>> Uh I learned over a period of time. Uh
originally I was a 22year-old uh out of
college uh drank way too much coffee. Um
was trying to do too many things at the
same time. I was very distracted, high
energy, trying to just get everything
done that I could possibly get done. I
went at a pace back in my 20s that I
could not keep up with today at 73. Um,
little by little I started uh increasing
what I would call self-awareness.
And it could be as simple as being on a
Zoom call or uh in this case Riverside
we're using today for this platform. If
I were to look at the screen and look at
myself talking, I can uh say, "Tom, you
should smile more." Or, "Tom, you should
be serious."
And I can change the way it looks. And I
can feel the the muscles in my face
doing different things. And so I know
just by thinking about it now what my
face looks like without having to look
at me talking on the screen. So that's a
bit of self-awareness and that's just a
small very small example of that. But it
could be everything from uh I started
recognizing tension in my fingers while
I was programming. That meant I was a
little bit more stressed. So I just go
like, you know, move my fingers, loosen
them up, and uh I'd feel more relaxed.
And so those were all just observations
of what's going on with your body, what
are you thinking, and all that. Well, in
trading as I went forward in my 20s and
got into the 30s even, which was before
I met Jack, uh you really ended up I I
ended up becoming decaffeinated. I ended
up uh continuing to try my best to
figure out how I could sort of read my
own mind on what what mental state was I
in. Was I getting excited? Was I getting
greedy? Was I getting fearful? Was I
getting angry? was a all these different
emotional states that people go through.
And I started realizing that I could u
choose to be balanced and calm
and think strategically
a lot more than I was doing. So I
started taking on that and it got easier
and easier as I kept working at it. And
eventually, I think I've told this story
before, I decided every half an hour, I
put a uh little what they call a post-it
note, you know, the little sticky note
thing. I stuck it on my screen.
>> And every time, you know, I I actually
would see that and it would say, "Be
aware."
And what that was a reminder to me of
just to go through a little bit of a
analysis of myself and was I aware of
everything that I was doing at that
point. And it kept reminding me over and
over again. So now like every 30 minutes
I'm doing this pretty soon after a few
weeks of doing that you find yourself
doing it continually because you don't
want the half an hour to come up and
then you have to uh you know ask the
question were you aware and answer no I
wasn't aware and then you have to kind
of kick yourself because I was supposed
to be aware and so little by little it
got easier and easier and now it's just
real time I pretty much am aware in the
middle of a golf swing. Yeah, it is.
I've been doing it for 50 years or
something. I don't know. It it So, but
it's a learned skill.
>> Got it. Got it. So, I've got to learn
that too because with these days, I'm
sure um the the number of distractions
that we have are way too many. Even when
we are working on a computer, we have
way too many tabs open. And I have that
bad habit of opening many tabs at a
given time. So, I think I need that
sticky note more than you do today. So,
>> yeah, you you finish a tab and you get
rid of it. I've got a total of uh well,
see, two of the tabs are for you guys
and I have three other tabs open.
>> Yeah, I've got to learn that. So um so
one of my questions which I had I I did
research a bit about you but I didn't
find much about what kind of a student
were you in school a little before you
got into college and what was your sense
uh of the markets at that point of time
or were you uh you had you know it's
quite possible that you had no sense of
the markets at that point of time but
I'm just curious what were you as a as a
high school student? a high school
student. I was third in my class of 103.
Uh got a lot of scholarships. I probably
had more scholarships than than
everybody else in the class. Uh so that
worked out pretty well to help me get
through college in chemical engineering
because I went to uh Clarkson
University, which is a private
university, and it it cost a lot more
than my uh parents could afford. So the
the scholarships really helped. Was
chemical engineering out of choice or
was that the in thing at that point of
time?
>> I loved chemistry. Uh still think it's
fascinating.
I liked organic chemistry the best even.
Uh but I I just like the sort of the
application. Math by itself to me was a
bit of a dry kind of interesting topic
and I was decent at it. I wouldn't say
I'm a brilliant mathematician or
anything but I understand math pretty
well and I but I understand it from this
the practical nature of what could you
apply this to. So uh for example uh when
you take integral calculus it's a very
esoteric thing and a lot of people are
bewildered by it but I immediately when
they started describing integral
calculus saw this lake and I was trying
to map the bottom of the lake and it uh
it's it's going all over the place. So
you're breaking the lake down into tiny
squares and integrating them together to
get the volume of the lake an
approximation. But that there's that's
kind of
taking sort of a dry subject like math
and applying it to the real world. And I
did the same thing in uh in various
maths uh and in chemical engineering.
The thermodynamics, fluid dynamics, all
these different aspects of chemical
engineering have a lot of math, but it
is actually trying to do something with
the math in in the real world to help
people or to produce a product or to
whatever, you know, and so it always
fascinated me and I loved chemistry. So
chemical engineering is the combination
of math and chemistry.
>> Lovely.
>> Made my decision. And and from Clarkson
you you joined Monsanto straight away.
>> Yes. Right out of school.
>> And what were you doing at Monsanto?
>> Uh we were doing industrial chemicals.
Uh I was helping to design new plants
and uh bottleneck
uh older plants that we needed more
capacity out of or we needed to uh back
in those days we were through the oil
embargo days. So every bit of energy
that we used in producing anything
needed to be very very efficient. So any
way of capturing escaping heat and using
it to preheat a feed stream or anything
was fair game. So we're always looking
for ways of squeezing down the uh
efficiency squeezing up the efficiency
of the process to either produce higher
quality product more product or uh
reduce the energy usage. And when did
markets happen during this phase? Was it
in college or was it after college?
>> High school. High school is when I
started buying my first mutual fund. Uh
but at that point I was not
at all
uh cognizant of market movement. I
wasn't tracking anything. I wasn't
charting anything. I was simply taking
uh monies that were coming in as I
worked on a part-time basis. either the
paper boy from 12 to 16. Uh I bought
mutual funds and then uh when I was 16
to 18 and graduating out of high school
and going to college, I
uh worked in a grocery store. So I
bagged groceries and stocked shelves and
brought carts in from the parking lot
and uh that type of thing. I every now
and again I would uh run to the bakery
to pick up a batch of Italian bread for
the for us to sell using the owner's
car. He trusted me to to drive his
Cadillac. Uh so a lot of good
experiences as a child uh before I got
out of high school and all this extra
money just kind of kept going into my
mutual fund account and it built up more
and more. Did someone tell you about in
I mean I'm
>> Yeah.
>> I'm I'm curious. A 16-year-old boy
investing in a mutual fund. Did you know
how did you figure that out?
>> Oh, it was as as I was 12 years old when
I started investing.
>> Okay.
>> Uh and how that happened was my father
who was a uh a postal delivery guy. He
he would walk around routes and deliver
people's mail. He uh some for some
reason, I'm not sure why, had a mutual
fund salesman from Fidelity back in
those days come to the house and he
listened to the sales pitch and I
listened to the sales pitch. I ended up
buying uh into the concept and decided
I'd put a little bit of my uh $10 a week
uh into this mutual fund. And it kept
building up and building up. And I
started uh seeing that it it got more
and more. First it was $100 and then it
was oh it got to be $500 and it got a
couple couple thousand dollar and and uh
I it really didn't dawn on me that much
that the prices went up and down as much
as they did until I got out of college
when I was graduating as a chemical
engineer. All of a sudden I looked at it
and said hm you know I put this much in
and it's worth that same amount because
of all the ups and downs. And I went
back and tracked it and I started
realizing that and I then really got
into charting and trying to sold out of
the mutual fund and started managing my
own money and use that as part of the
seed capital to start my own account.
>> Interesting. And at that time what did
charting mean?
Because we did not have these electronic
tools I'm assuming.
>> Yeah, that's for sure. I did a wore my
eyes out and my uh my poor fingers from
holding on to a pencil and charting. Uh
I would have chart paper. Everything
would be done with a ruler and a little
bit of a stroke of the pencil. And maybe
once a week or so you'd put a date down
at the bottom so you keep track of where
you are. Uh things like point and figure
charting uh compress lots of history
onto a smaller page. So, a lot of uh the
people today trading probably may have
never even heard of point and figure
charts, but uh when we started out, that
was a pretty uh widely popular way of
charting because you could compress the
price data into
uh a smaller amount of space. And to
this day, I use a concept of combining
together bar charts with point and
figure. And I call it point and figure
bar. uh and uh I just combine the two
concepts together. It's just something
that works in my brain. It's not
important. It's not magical. It's not uh
uh the magic bullet or anything. It's
going to have the same types of
statistics as a Kelner band or a Boinger
band or a
Donin channels and lots of other things.
It's just slightly different wrinkle to
it. But when I got started doing that, I
started realizing I looked down at a
bunch of charts. I actually was starting
up my commodities trading at that point.
I was very successful in stock trading
and I I put a bunch of charts down on
the floor and I was up on the sofa
looking down at the floor at all these
charts and I I could say, "Wow, that
that move in live cattle was crazy. That
move over here in gold was nuts. You
could pick that up. You'd make a lot of
money." And I started realizing what
were the common threads between these
and I was doing viewing it from a uh
point and figure uh you know view and
when I decided okay if I just get in on
every breakout I don't care what it
looks like I'm just going to jump in on
it and ignore the news ignore the
analysts. Um, I'm going to pick up every
one of those and they're going to pay so
much money that I can make losses on all
the other false breakouts and uh it'll
work. And so I set out to do that. And
um that probably was a few years a year
to two years into the process and
another
>> when was this which year would
>> this would have been back in the 70s. Uh
probably around 76 to 80 right in there.
or some place
and it took four years but on the fourth
year I uh actually got to where I was
finally slightly profitable
and uh at that point it just got better
and better.
>> And um you know since we're talking
about markets did you read some books
did you um were there people whose ideas
influenced you right in the beginning in
those four years? Yeah, the Mark Douglas
books on the psychology of trading. Uh I
can't even remember the name of them
now, but he's no long
>> Yeah, Trading in the Zone is definitely
one of them and there's a couple of
others he wrote. All of them are really
good. Uh I did I do like now I don't
know if it was done then. I think it was
probably more in the 80s, but uh Trade
Your Way to Financial Freedom is a great
book by Tharp.
uh he
covers the three things the three
general areas that I think are important
for traders to understand that they have
to deal with one is how do you buy and
sell that's the whole I call it the
buyell engine you got an an engine moves
the car the trade the buy sell engine's
got to move the trader and and make them
buy or sell uh but you got to know how
much to buy and sell so that's the
second part You got to size your
positions. You have to maintain your
positions. I I I would argue throughout
the time that you own it. It's not just
initially sizing the positions. It's
also looking ongoing at what kind of
position do you have. If you bought
Nvidia at 10 and it's now whatever with
all the the price movement it's had over
the last few years. Well, if you haven't
adjusted that position, then you have a
Nvidia portfolio with a couple little
decimal points of other things in there
and that's not a balanced portfolio. So,
you you have to come to grips with how
do you uh manage your ongoing. And then
the third area he covers and and I would
say Tharp is an expert in it or was an
expert. He's no longer with us either.
Is the area of psychology. The mental
processes in trading are
so potentially overwhelming that a lot
of traders get caught up in all sorts of
mind traps that uh you really have to
try to understand yourself very well. I
think trading is the one thing in my
life that's taught me so much about
myself. Uh very fascinating uh education
I would say. And all three of those
areas have to be in place to be a
successful trader I think.
>> Right. So um talking about trend
following was there um a natural
inclination that you had towards trend
following or did you explore during
these four years different kinds of
trading across different time frames and
then you know figured out that trend
following works better for you. So, how
did that the evolution of trend
following in your mind? How did that
happen?
>> I would say at first I was a little bit
more trying to be a fundamental guy
trying to understand the supply and
demand of a market or the the
fundamentals of a company if I was
buying shares
and the process was I didn't have a lot
of time. The process was very
timeconuming. So, I felt like I really
couldn't spend the time I wanted to
spend on doing some of this stuff. And I
realized that in the end, the guys on
Wall Street have staffs of people and
computers that I don't have, mainframes
back in those days. PC hadn't even been
invented yet. And uh so it really became
sort of um
what can I do to pick up on the move
that is going to happen ac if I look at
all these different things across the
board.
This one might be the next one that goes
that one over there might be the next
big one. And I don't know how I'm going
to predict which one. So, if I can just
look at those price movements and the
big guys are pushing it and breaking it
out through an indicator of some sort
and if I could jump on quickly then and
do it in a disciplined fashion, I should
be able to capture a lot of that move.
And so, I didn't even know at the time
there wasn't a term called trend
following back then. It was just to me
jumping on the uh so many moves that uh
you know looking for some to come out in
my favor and lo and behold maybe 10
years after that people started calling
it trend following I guess but it was to
me it was just trying to jump on moves
and it was a sort of playing a
statistical game of these 30% of the
moves are going to be very profitable
the 70% or 66% or so are going to be
losers and I'm going to try to you
minimize them as much as possible. And
out of the 33% or so that are
profitable, perhaps a few percent like
less than five will be humongously way
way way profitable. And those are the
ones where you're in for a year, year
and a half, and it's up hundreds of
percent. That pays for an awfully lot
awful lot of losses. And uh I think
that's what I
locked on to early on and uh just kept
running it for what 45 50 years now.
>> Got it. So you said you would you know
you you started off being a fundamental
person but then when we talk about
commodities there's no fundamentals
there it's it's largely demand and
supply. So there different thing. Yeah
there is
>> there there are some fundamentals but
yeah.
>> Okay. Yep.
>> So how did you get started with
commodities? What was the idea behind
getting into commodities?
>> It was diversification. Uh when I
started out the world was uh you know
the Indian market was a lot younger.
Japan market was out there. there were
some uh stock markets in Europe and the
correlation amongst the various indexes
around the world were running maybe in
the sixes
uh high 6s and stuff like that. I mean
it was they were there was a decent
amount of diversification.
So you could put a portfolio together
and you could do some US stocks and some
Japanese stocks and maybe some London
stocks and you know get a little bit of
diversification
as computers came in. 1980 the PCs
really start taking over the world. Uh
the AT a couple years later everything
just blew skyhigh. What ended up
happening I observed the indices around
the world started becoming more
intercorrelated.
people were able to just transmit an
order to Japan real easily. It didn't
involve calling a broker and people
sending teletypes and all of the
nonsense. So if uh New York was up that
day, Tokyo tended to be up that way uh
that that that evening for us morning
for you uh over in the Far East. And
then you'd get London and and Germany
and France all kind of up and then you'd
go back to New York and start over again
for another 24 hours. And now you look
at the world and you're up into the
almost like high point8s on the
correlation maybe 0.9 it's become very
very correlated. So for me, I was just
looking for a way uh you know, if the
stock market were to go through a 50
cent on a dollar down, 50% decline, I
didn't want to be just totally oriented
towards stocks. I was asking myself,
what could I trade that, you know, might
go up during that period or might uh I'd
be able to make a profit. And so things
like gold were interesting. Silver had a
big run when the Hunts tried to corner
it uh way back when. U there was lots of
big moves that happened in commodities
>> just the way it's happening right now.
>> Yeah. Well, frosts in uh Florida for
orange juice, coffee having a problem
with a frost in Brazil and the crop is
looking to be small and you know there
lots of different things that are going
on. And when you sit back just not as a
statistician, just as a human being, a
logical thinking person, and you ask
yourself, what does coffee care about
what the S&P 500 is doing? Nothing. They
are diversified. They're two different
completely different markets. One could
go up and the other one goes up. One
could go up, the other one goes down.
The two have nothing to do with each
other. And you could say the same about,
let's say, live cattle and uh the the
euro.
What th those aren't going to have a
heck of a lot of So, if you're trading
live cattle and you're trading euros,
you got a diversified portfolio. So, it
led me to to put together more
diversified futures portfolios because
there's just a lot more opportunity to
get away from just stocks. I still trade
lots of equity indexes, so I have
exposure to stocks. That's one of the
many things I trade. But I have lots of
other things and grains and meats and
metals and industrial metals and
currencies and debt instruments and
energy and you know you can get pretty
widely diversified very quickly in the
futures markets where it's hard to do
that in stocks anymore.
>> Got it. So, so during this phase when
now you have a sense of the markets,
you're doing commodities, you you
already done equity and now we have
computers. At what point did you realize
that looking at the markets through the
lens of a a rule set or being systematic
about the markets is the way to go. So
at what point did you you know build
that conviction? Uh usually at the
school of hard knocks uh called the uh
trading university uh I would catch
myself doing something that was not part
of my strategy. Uh either through just a
simple human mistake or some kind of a
um
a mental flaw at the time uh an
impulsive decision or something. And I
say, "Wait a second, that Tom, that's
not what you're supposed to be doing."
And so I kept thinking to myself, how
can I sort of take myself as a human
being full of the ability to make
mistakes and have emotional decisions
and all that? How can I reduce the uh
the impact of me? And I started
realizing as I started just making my
day more efficient. Like it could be
something as simple as you're trading
along and you do trade after trade and
you're always doing a thousand shares of
some of this next stock that you're
doing and so you just get on autopilot.
You start doing a thousand and a
thousand and a thousand and you just
keep going and you're not thinking too
much about but one's a $10 stock, the
other one's a $20 stock. So you just on
the $20 stock, you just bought twice as
much. Or maybe you buy 500, you always
buy just uh you know the same dollar
amount. Well, that's not that that's
treating them all the same in terms of
dollars, but one might move twice the
speed to the other. So you just got
twice the impact to your portfolio from
the volatile one versus the quieter
stock. So, I started realizing that if I
could just put the parameters of the
trade into a little spreadsheet, it
could spit back to me the exact number
of shares that I should do to keep the
portfolio completely balanced in every
position equal. And as you start
realizing that little bit of automation
all of a sudden saves you pounding a
calculator, potentially hitting the
wrong button and making a mistake, it
automates it a little bit and and it
starts opening this world of automation
to you and saying, "Wow, you know, I
could put bring in my prices instead of
looking at the screen and writing it
down on a piece of paper. I could uh pay
a little money and go to this database
and download it. And then once I
download it, I have it so I can get rid
of this piece of paper stuff. And once I
have the prices here, I could actually
run this uh instead of me looking at a
chart and deciding that's where I'm
supposed to buy, I could tell the
computer how to do that and I get rid of
that part of my job. And I I was just
basically trying to put myself out of
work. And little by little, then you
squeeze the error rate down. You're
doing the same thing you were supposed
to be doing in the first place, but
you're doing it by hitting a button on a
computer and the computer's doing all
the drudgery, the the manual,
you know, calculating the same thing
over and over again to the point of
boredom. And that allows me to think
more globally, invent new ways to trade,
invent new programs to keep track of
things or to do research studies.
That's more creative human endeavor and
a lot more fun. uh the the actual
running of the orders every day is the
least exciting thing I do every day.
>> I get that. So going back to your
spreadsheet days, was were you back
testing on spreadsheets at that point of
time or how did this whole idea of be it
rules or be it back testing, how how was
it done at that point of time? Wall
Street Journal in a pile.
Pull a price. Put it down on a sheet of
paper.
Put the Wall Street over here. Get the
next one. Open it up. Write down the
price. Get that all done. Take uh
several years of doing that. Your hands
are now black from ink off the paper.
And then what you do is you take all
these sheets of uh ledger paper that
you've written down all these prices and
you start translating them into uh chart
paper. So you take a ruler and you move
it over one little square and you draw a
new line and a new line, a new line and
you make all that happen. And then you
assess using uh whatever the indicator
like point figure or whatever you were
doing. You would then try to uh do a
trading summary by writing down the date
of a buy, a date of a sell, how much did
you make or lose, and then you'd uh
eventually have that study complete. It
might take weekends over and over, like
two or three weekends of very hard work,
uh tired eyes,
uh to get a study done and realize that
uh you know, this makes some sense to
me. It just makes logical sense. I'm
going to go ahead and start trading this
way. There were no computers. I did this
uh primarily in the 70s. So 74 I came
out of university. Uh about 1980 I got
my first PC and that that's when I
started automating uh more in the
computer and then things happened fast
after that.
>> Did you get prizes uh was there
databases on through which you could get
prizes into uh a spreadsheet? Uh yeah,
back then in 1980 I was able to tie into
uh some of the I would call them r crude
uh databases for a little bit of money.
Um it got better and better and has
continually gotten better. Now there's
multiple places you can try to get data
from and some of it for free, some of it
for a modest amount. Um, but the
historical data now is so much superior
to where uh it was back when 1980 rolled
around and people were clamoring for
data so they could put it on their
computers. But the database companies
hadn't been keeping track of it. So then
they were scrambling to try to figure
out, well, how can we get 10 years of
history so these people can buy it from
us?
>> Buy it.
>> But they did they hadn't been keeping
it. So, um, they had people were
scrambling to try to figure out it was a
it was the wild wild west.
>> I I I I can I I get a sense of what it
was.
>> And also the data the data had flaws.
You had to run
>> I'm sure
>> data checks uh I I would find
>> I would run a check like here's the high
or low for the day and the high and low
and the open was here
up up above the high. How
>> how can I
>> the high and low it can't or the close
the close is below the low can't happen.
So you'd spit it out and you'd have to
go back and try to make sense of what
was going on and what would be a logical
answer to the data and correct the data
and go back to the database company and
say, you know, you got some screwy data
in here. You might want to check that
again. So it was data integrity was a
real problem
and uh the PCs back then were I mean
this is like Windows one not Windows 11
you know many many operating systems ago
and uh it was pretty rudimentary it was
there wasn't a lot you could do with it
uh but it was better than a calculator
and then uh the AT was I don't know I
want to say three to four times as fast
and capable so I bought the AT right
when it came out and loved that and that
really pushed us forward quite a bit.
And then uh after that I just kept
adding more and more PCs and we ended up
with a lot of Dells and
some computers that didn't even have
screens. We'd um set them up so we could
uh do a switch from one screen to like
four different computers and just switch
to every one we wanted so that we didn't
have to buy a bunch of monitors and
consume the electricity and and all
that. So we were running server banks
before they were server banks. I guess
we were stacked
>> stacked them up. We had uh we had had
good air conditioning in our little
office at Trenstat. So uh so so if I go
back to those days, was there a trading
system that um you were running? I'm
sure there was. And what was that? Can
you give me the the you know in a in a
rudimentary sense? What what exactly was
that first trading system that you had?
>> In a rudiment frame were you trading?
>> In a rudimentary sense, I was using
point and figure philosophy
on bar charts. So u for example X's go
up on point and figure O's go down.
>> Yes.
>> So I would let the bar you know the bar
chart would run up. That's a row of X's.
It would peek out and go the other way.
So that would be the kind of the top of
the X run. sort of like uh what people
call swing trading where they're uh the
swing highs and lows if you're trying to
trade the range would also be conversely
the breakouts if you were trying to
trend follow it. So if you try to stay
inside those peaks and valleys that's uh
kind of what sideways trading or swing
trading. If you break the swing highs
and lows that would be more like
breakouts. So, that's kind of what we
were doing. Pretty long-term trend
following, not a specific time frame. We
let the charts tell us where that was
and just go with it. But we could all
always measure the risk on the trade,
the volatility on the trade, properly
size our positions, cover lots and lots
of markets, which a lot of traders
because of their they were doing it
human uh driven. Uh as a human being,
you're limited to how much you can
handle. you just can't process, you
know, a lot of stuff.
>> Computers, you know, 200 markets is no
problem.
>> So, so can we call it was something on a
daily time frame or would you want to
call it a weekly time frame because you
were um I I know you were on point and
figure so so the aspect of time may not
be relevant. It's more price than time
there. So, but how did you at what point
would you go back you know what was the
interval at which you would go back and
check prices?
>> The uh it would be daily and remember
that we're using point and figure bar.
The bar is daily. We're using point and
figure concepts over top of the bar. So
that's why I call it PF bar.
>> Um so it's a it's a kind of a blend
between the two. But we'd update daily,
get new prices, new orders, cancel and
replace the entire set of orders. Uh, so
a lot of orders were going in. We had
like a few hundred clients and $600
million and 40 computers and 10 people
and a lot of stuff happening.
>> Interesting. So um so if you now that
you've seen 1980s and how trend
following was then and then 90s 2000 all
the way till today a lot of times when I
speak with people who uh who who do
trend following this they observe
something called an edge decay which
means the same strategy when run over a
given instrument the returns kind of
reduce over a period of time did you
observe something like that or do you
observe that phenomena
>> I don't observe oberve it as much as a
lot of people seem to think there is.
But I do observe that those trends
happen quicker. My theory of the whole
world as I've observed it over the last
50 years is that computers have reduced
the time for everything to happen. So,
we go back to when I would do my first
futures trade and I call the broker and
want to buy two corn and he's got to
write it up on a piece of paper and he's
got to run it down to the teletype
operator. Teletype goes to the floor.
The floor gives it to a runner. The
runner runs it out to the pit, hands it
to the guy. He does the hand signals.
They get the execution. He writes down
who he sold it or bought it from. Drops
it down on the floor. The runner climbs
under the pit, gets the piece of paper,
takes it back, and about a half an hour
later, if I'm lucky, the broker gets
something in his inbox, calls me, and
says, "You got your fill." Nowadays, I'm
on one screen over here with my trading
platform. If I were to do a market order
on two corn, by the time I hit the
transmit button and turned my head to
there, the bottom of my right screen
over here would be a little message
saying you just executed two corn.
That's how fast everything is. And I'm
in Arizona, nowhere near the Chicago
pits or anything. So, the world's a
different place. And because of that
ability to move larger contracts through
very small amounts of time, every
movement of the market can be
accelerated
far greater than it could ever be back
in the 1970s because in the 70s you just
had a lot of impediments to getting
things done. You had to work hard to
move the money.
>> Nowadays it's you can do it on your
phone. It's ridiculous. So from anywhere
in the world, you guys in India can
trade around the world. I can trade
India. It's getting to be a very small
world out there. And I think because of
that um bare market that back in 7374
in S&P uh down 50% in those two years.
Now you can do say down 35 during COVID
in about a month, month and a half and
it has the same horrifying,
you know, scares the living daylights
out of everybody. Um, so it has the same
psychological effect of being a bare
market, but it's compressed down into
instead of two years, it's only 35%, but
it happens so quickly it scares the wits
out of everybody.
And uh then it turns around and makes
new highs. Just one more bare market.
I've lived through a lot of them over
the years. But my thesis is that all of
this stuff's happening with much much
greater volatility. So you need to you
need to think through how you deal with
greater volatility and size your
positions properly and be careful.
>> I I get that. So, so in a sense what
you're saying is since things are
happening faster, does it mean we have
shorter trends and you know how does it
change the structure of the market in
terms of pullbacks in terms of um you
know how the way the trend would
manifest in a given product or an
instrument?
>> Um I think there's the potential
through speed of motion to have more
psychological impact in a smaller amount
of time. So my thesis is is that yes,
the time that the trends persist uh
could be a bit shorter, but then you get
situations like we're in now in the US
where the stock market just keeps kind
of making new highs and making new highs
and and every pullback becomes a buying
opportunity for some who want to buy the
dip. And I hear that on the morning news
all the time. You got to buy the dip.
Buy the dip. Buy the dip. I mean, at
some point you're going to buy the dip
and it's going to keep going down and
you're going to regret buying the dip.
But right now, that's working great. I
think uh you still have to have the
psychological euphoria of a good market
and you need to have the psychological
horror of a bare market. And I think
those are uh able to happen a lot
quicker than they used to.
>> I want to get to something more specific
when I ask that question. So let's say
you you follow a breakout system or you
follow a moving average kind of system
to identify trends. Does that mean the
kind of parameters which worked 20 years
back or 30 years back are not the
parameters which would work today and
you would have to kind of reset the
parameters for today's volatility for
today's trends. Can you help me
structure that thought? The answer to me
is make your indicators include things
like volatility so that as volatility
gets greater your indicators adjust
themselves. So if you examine the math
behind a math is dry but if you can make
math practical I like it. Uh so if you
look at the math behind say a simple
donin channel which I use a lot because
it's simple to describe it. It's the
high of say the last 21 days and the low
of the last 21 days. Well,
>> yep.
>> If you use 21 days and that's about a
month of trading
including holidays and whatever. So, you
got you got this uh kind of uh top and
bottom band of the donins and the
highest high and the lowest low. Well,
if volatility gets greater,
>> guess what happened to the don channels?
It got wider.
>> So, it adjusts itself over time.
And I like indicators like that. I don't
like things like um say a hardwired
50-day moving average
a or a 21-day moving average. That is a
very specific time parameter. And
everything that happens within 21 days
is going to be into the average. And
then the daily prices or whatever other
indicator you might use to go across the
21 days is is becoming more volatile.
and you're not adjusting at all for
that. That's worrisome. But things like
Kelner adjust, things like Bowlinger re
adjust,
>> my point and figure bar adjusts, my Don
adjusts, all of those have that same
volatility inherent adjustment to their
indicator uh math that takes into
account changing conditions, which I
think is over time a lot more robust it
seems to me.
>> Makes sense. Did you ever use moving
averages and what what's your um you
know thought on that?
>> I did use moving averages very very
early on and my thought on that was uh
when I went back and tried to do an
optimization of the moving averages to
figure out what would be the optimum,
it would always change. And so I
thought, well, how can I do something
with this that changes automatically
because this is not working. And that's
when I I saw Kelner uh could use the
average true range on the top and bottom
of a moving average and therefore expand
or contract with changing volatility.
And I thought ah that's the way to go.
Used it as the basis and then top and
bottom
do the uh average two range bands on
either side of it and that gives you
that flexibility with changing market
conditions.
and I abandon rigid uh moving averages
kind of stuff.
>> Got it.
>> So,
>> so uh so moving to I mean I I was
listening to one of your interviews and
uh you speak about something a concept
called filling the potholes where among
the other trend following strategies you
kind of also have some mean reversion
strategies. So um could you help me
understand what kind of strategies are
those and what what are we what are we
trying to do in those strategies?
>> Okay. I don't do mean reversion myself.
It is a good alternative to use to fill
potholes. Lawrence Benorp whose book is
like right there um as a friend and he
does a lot of multiple trading strategy
uh research and and I think he trades
like 56 trading strategies
simultaneously. I credit him with the
term fill the pothole. It's not my term
but I like it. It it gives me the image
of the track record going up the page
and then a draw down happening. And
that's the pothole and I want to fill it
>> and uh yeah draw downs are not fun for
anybody. If you look at a lot of those
potholes with trend following you
realize that mean reversion strategies
many times can help fill that pothole.
Lawrence does it a number of different
ways. The way I deal with the same
situation
is, for example, let's say I take a
21-day don
strategy and I've got the typical
long-term trend following draw down that
you're going to see in any kind of trend
following strategy. Then what I'm going
to do is pair that same markets, same
portfolio. I'm going to pair it with
maybe a three-day indicator, three-day
don or something.
So, if you think about what happens,
let's say you have a big run in gold and
it's right at the high of all time.
You're making tons of money on your
long-term strategy, but your short-term
strategy on a 3-day basis is ready to go
short. So, the market comes off that
peak and immediately your short-term
strategy goes short. So, you got one up,
you got the other one down,
>> other down
>> and you kind of cancels each other. kind
of cancel the other and you've you've
taken the risk way down. You've improved
your return to risk ratios, which is I'm
a big fan of. If you are a return guy,
I'll freely say if you're trying to make
your first billion by the time you're
30, this is not the way to go. You want
to have the wild ride and make as much
money as possible. So, if you're
shooting for returns and that's your
only goal, ignore what I'm saying. But
if you're like me, retired, 73 years
old, I just want smooth, you want a good
return to risk ratio. What by doing
that, what you're doing is eliminating
the first part of a draw down in the
trend following strategy because you're
at zero position.
Then if it continues down,
your long-term strategy is going to kick
in and now you're full boore two
strategies short making a bunch of
money. What I find when I do that uh you
do use the long-term and short term uh
marrying together helps the return to
risk ratio a great deal.
>> Interesting. So something you know some
people call it multi-time frame.
>> Uh
>> yeah.
>> So that's what it is.
>> And I do it across 30 plus markets.
>> I'm just curious how do you track all
your positions today? So I'm sure it's
easier than what you did that time.
>> Yeah. I don't do it by hand anymore. I
you can pull in your positions. You can
pull in your
>> um you know the various uh the markets
and uh have have a computer actually go
through and say do all these positions
that the broker says that I have are
they really what I have? You know, tell
you the exceptions. Say, hey, you better
check the uh uh the copper market looks
weird here. you're supposed to have uh
two short and you only have one short.
So then you go in and investigate and
try to figure out what happened.
>> Moving to um Tom, moving to position
sizing. I I I was listening to some of
your interviews and
you had some thoughts in terms of how
how you position size based on u
volatility. Then I I I had a follow-up
question on that. What I want to know is
I if this idea of position sizing
evolved over time and what were those
triggers based on which you changed your
thinking about position sizing?
>> Uh my position sizing at first was
highly affected by reading the first
market wizards book by Schwagger uh on
Larry Height uh of Mint. Mint was one of
our largest CTAs back in the day when I
first started, Commodity Trading
Advisor. They were handling about a
billion dollars and that was back in
1980.
So that was worth a lot of money.
>> And uh Larry was not
uh I would call a rocket scientist. He
was more of a street smart guy. And it
just made sense to him that you got to
make the bet size the same on every bet
that you make. So he was into the sort
of the gamblers's philosophy uh of
approaching the markets, the statistics
of making your bet size equivalent each
time. And that's what they were doing.
And when I heard him say the term bet
size in the interview,
um he was referring to the amount of
money you could lose. So therefore,
mathematically that would be where
you're getting in versus where your stop
loss is. So once I knew that that he was
making that the same each time, I
thought, all right, well, if it's the
same, it's got to be a percent of the
equity somehow. So I started doing risk
as a percent of equity. And that worked
beautifully and it improved my return to
risk when I did the studies. So I said,
okay, we'll make that definitely part of
the the programs. But then I started um
along the way we had a silver trade that
we got into and the volatility was just
unbelievable. When the trade started
out, it wasn't. But when the trade kept
going, it was getting very, very
volatile. And I was experimenting with
things with average true range at the
time. And I thought to myself, well, you
know, if this was volatility, the speed
of movement is psychologically
affecting our clients because when
markets move a lot, they're calling up
and wanting to know what we're doing and
all that. They're getting nervous. So,
it isn't just the risk of losing money.
It's also the speed at which an
investment moves that becomes a sort of
risk factor in people's brains. So I
need to think about controlling the
volatility. So then I started saying
well what if we did uh risk calculation
and a volatility calculation both as a
percent of equity then take the smaller
of the two whatever the answer is. You
know this one we go buy 10 contracts.
This one says to buy eight. We buy
eight.
uh whatever the lowest number calculated
and then we added to that margin because
there's some markets like Euro dollars
and other things that some markets that
have a lot higher margin for the amount
of movement. So the risk is low the
volatility is low but every now and
again you get these big jumps
and the margin people know that you get
those big jumps so they protect
themselves in the exchanges by putting a
higher margin on it. So we did margin to
equity as well. Once we had all three in
place, we never had a situation where we
were all that embarrassed because we had
positions sized every day across the
portfolios across we were at the peak we
were trading like 75 markets or
something.
It was easy to do with the computers and
we could spread that risk uh a great
deal. And I think that that's where we
brought the volatility into the
calculation. I think was really
impactful at smoothing things out and
particularly you know you know where
volatility comes in later in a trade.
You start out markets are quiet nobody
cares. It breaks out. You've got a small
amount of risk
and so here's your buying in here.
Here's your stop-loss point. The market
takes off. Fundamentalists are start
trying to predict what why it's going
up. trend followers are jumping on,
people reading the news are jumping on.
Everybody's getting excited. Now all of
a sudden this has gone to now every day
we're doing that. So as volatility
increases throughout the maturity of a
really successful trade and everybody
gets excited. measuring the volatility
as a percent of equity becomes important
because that gives you the excuse to
say, "Yeah, you're getting a little bit
too much volatility in your portfolio
due to this one position." So, if I
squeeze down the position size a little
bit, I have less impact of the
portfolio. And as it turns out, you're
taking profits too uh as a as a plus.
But I don't look at it that way. I look
at it as managing the volatility and the
risk.
>> Got it. Got it. Lovely. So um there's
another thing which I uh you know read
and probably listened to in one of your
podcasts and you refer to the idea of
law of large numbers and you know can
you help me put that idea in perspective
in what context u do you think it's
helpful to traders and how did you
benefit from it? The simple way of
putting it to the mental side of the
trader is any one trade is just one data
point in your next 10,00 trades. I say
that over and over again.
>> Uh that's the way I truly think of it.
If you [clears throat] have an edge and
you know that doing your simulations,
you make $1.25
for every $1 you lose over a lot of
period of time. you want to get to that
thousand trades and net your $1.25
dollars per trade. Um, so any one trade
would be just an a single could
potentially be aberrant piece of data
uh that may go your way, may not go your
way, but it's not all that important.
It's the important thing is to get to a
thousand. So just keep on doing what
you're doing. Keep putting another trade
on. Keep collecting more and more data
and allow that expectation to expectancy
to come to real life. That's the way I
would describe it generically and simply
so that people could understand.
>> I I get that. But I have another point
there. So let's say um you have multiple
trading strategies and there's one
strategy which kind of is more active
than the other. So one would give you
more opportunities, the other one would
give you lesser. So if you were to kind
of
>> uh look at it from a law of large
numbers, there's one strategy which
gives you more opportunities, but it
also means there's more cost to trading,
right? I mean, if we if we kind of
>> uh So how do you put that aspect into
this? How do you build that in when we
talk about
>> we actually at Trendstat we kept track
of every trade and exactly what the
costs were to that trade. So there's the
cost of the bid s spread there's the
cost and and that really reflects in the
uh like if you put your stop at um 450
and you got filled at 4.60 60 the
slippage was uh 010.
Uh there's [clears throat] also the
slippage due to the commissions. So
maybe you're charged X dollars in
commissions to do the trade. So that's
commission slippage. There's also if
you're doing Forex, there's also the uh
time slippage uh because you're doing
forward. So, we call it forward slippage
because you're probably doing it spot or
at least the broker that you're working
with or bank you're working with is
doing the spot price and then they're
forward pricing it out to the end of the
month or wherever and they'll they'll
add on a slippage there. So, we would
track all three of those and then when
we did simulations of history, we would
use those actual numbers on each market.
So, if you're trading something like red
rice in Tokyo, you're going to have a
really big slippage number in there. And
when you do the simulation, you're going
to realize you're going to lose money
all the time. Uh it seems uh if you
trade something like uh US Treasury
bonds, you're not going to get a whole
lot of slippage. It's going to be very
minimal because the market is so deep.
And uh so that's kind of the way we take
care of it. on the simulations we
actually try to put some money in there
for those markets. So today when you
look at um a back test or a strategy are
there some key metrics that you focus on
let's say if I have to ask you about
your top four or five metrics you look
at them and say you know that that's
your first you know view of that
strategy what would that be
>> I would say the first thing I look at is
the maximum draw down
and then uh I would say
I would probably look at a simple very
crude uh what was the average return to
the maximum draw on which is like the
MAR ratio M
ratio. Then another metric that I like
that I invented myself was is called the
enjoy the ride or ETR comfort ratio. And
what that is is an integration of all of
the up days that you're at new highs or
not in a severe draw down, let's say,
where you're plotting along and clients
would be happy and you as a trader would
be just comfortable with it. That's the
comfort area. And then the discomfort
area is when you go beyond a certain
threshold of a draw down magnitude wise
and you go down a long enough time
threshold where it's getting old. So it
could be something like I'm good down to
10% I don't care. Uh anything less than
6 months I don't care. So you set some
thresholds. Anything over that amount
you're in discomfort zone and you
integrate those together every day. And
by doing that and you put the comfort
over the discomfort, you have a comfort
ratio. And I like to look at that from
the standpoint the higher higher the
better. And uh so I use that measurement
sometimes too when I'm
>> it's a ratio of time.
>> It's a ratio over the time period
measured particularly useful when
comparing one strategy versus another
strategy.
How comfortable would you be as a trader
running these two things side by side?
And what happens when you combine them
together? Maybe what happens to the
comfort ratio when I take a long-term
strategy and put it with a very
short-term strategy, where does the
comfort ratio go? And what you'll find
is if you use comfort ratio as a measure
of return to risk, you'll very clearly
see how you can improve your return to
risk ratios and make you as a a trader
more serene. So you could be Mr.
Serenity too.
>> Absolutely. We all aspire to be. So um
so other than that, any other ratios? So
we we spoke about
>> Well, I think sharp is okay.
>> Useless. Um, I can't understand how the
heck
>> somebody
>> uh well to me it's useless because it's
standard deviation. It's what it's
saying is that uh movement of price and
returns is somehow bad.
>> Bad and that's [clears throat] what you
want actually.
>> It is. Yes. Exactly. And especially in
an up market,
>> uh it penalizes a move up like if you
were to make 100%.
>> You're penalized on your sharp ratio
because you made too much money too
quickly and it runs the denominator up.
So Sortino attempts to take care of
that, but it's still using only
volatility as a measurement and it's
negative volatility as a measurement of
>> on the downside.
>> Yeah.
>> So it still doesn't quite capture it.
So, some of these types of I guess
measurements that are on the normal
packages out there, I you know, I
they're there. I can glance at them, but
I don't really think they're that
useful.
>> I prefer to my comfort ratios a lot more
getting at the heart of what you should
be looking at as a trader, I think.
>> Makes sense. Makes sense. So, that uh
Tom, that brings me to the next
question. you you've been a systematic
trader, but then have there been moments
where you said, "I don't trust what the
system tells me, but I need to take my
own call." So, have there been moments
of discretion? And how did you deal with
that is is my next question. After using
discretion back in the 70s and miserably
failing at it, I I don't do that. uh
during COVID for instance a lot of
commodity trading advisors literally
shut down their programs. They thought
the world was coming to an end. The
markets are insane. We are no longer
trade until this settles down.
I just kept trading and did the same
exact thing I'm doing today.
ended up short a lot of stuff in the
crash of COVID and ended up getting
signals to go in long when the vaccine
uh the the jabs were rolled out across
the world and we thought we were saved
maybe markets went crazy up I ended up
making 103% that year doing nothing
other than just following what I'm doing
now
and believe me that is I don't ever
expect to see that kind of return again
in my lifetime. Markets lined up
perfectly with everything I was doing is
just sheer aberant
multiple standard deviation.
>> Absolutely.
>> Uh performance way way beyond what I
would expect. I would expect you know 15
20% would be a good year for me. 103 is
insane. But it points to the just doing
what you're doing and understanding
enough about it to be comfortable in an
environment that's scaring the heck out
of everybody else.
>> Makes sense. In fact, my next question
on my list was about CO. I'm so glad you
brought that up because so um but you
answered my question and um talking
about discretion, there's something
which I tell people around me. I have a
a kind of an inverse win rate with
discretion. Every time I take a
discretionary call, I am damn sure it's
not going to work in my favor. So I
usually tell my friends or people around
me that I'm making a discretionary call
and I'm going to be wrong and I'm always
wrong. So I got I've got to kind of
invert my discretion. So that's that's
been my uh you know that's how it's been
for me. That can get very confusing
after a couple of, you know, like I'm
thinking this, so I should do the
opposite of that. But boy, that doesn't
feel very comfortable. That
>> I would that could also mess your head
up pretty badly. So I would
>> Yes.
>> I would guard against doing too much of
that.
>> No, it it's it's more in terms of how
bad my discretion always is. So it never
works. That That's what I want to say.
So u talking about co yeah I'm I'm I'm
I'm glad everything worked out and
things went fine but then had would have
would it have been or well let's say was
it ever possible I'm sure that you know
you there was some kind of a tail risk
which was not factored into your system
and did you have that fear did you think
about it and if you did was there a way
to deal with it other and diversifying
across different assets.
>> Yeah, my position sizing kicked in big
time. Uh, as the stuff was going down,
my stops were not coming down as fast as
they they usually would because well,
think about it. A 21-day dungeon, for
example, you go into the COVID crash.
So, the the top and the bottom is here.
Well, the COVID crash happens. So now
>> this is going all the way down. But 21
days
>> later,
>> the highest high is still up here.
Hasn't moved.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> But now a Kelner, the Kelner is based on
a moving average exponential I use. It
starts getting dragged down with prices
and the stops move. So, I had some
indicators
moving down the stops fast, but still
they're not keeping up with the vol the
velocity that was prices were crashing.
The indicators couldn't possibly keep
up. So, the risk and the volatility kept
screaming upward.
So, let's say if you start with a
position of 10 contracts short, you're
making a lot of money, but the
volatility is exponentially getting
bigger and the risk is now getting
bigger because you can't move the stops
down fast enough. So, you run the
calculation every day and says, "No, you
really should have only eight contracts
now." So, I peel two off. Then, the next
day, the same thing happens. It says,
"Probably should only have seven now."
Peel another one off. you know, by the
end of the run down, you might be down
to five or something. And so, you got
half the position that you had
initially, but you got a market that's
two, three times as volatile, and the
risk is yet to catch up. And then when
the market starts actually rallying, now
the risk is plummeting because the stops
are still coming down. The market prices
are coming up to meet the stop price.
So, the risk is low, but the volatility
is high. So it's peeling off contract
still potentially. Eventually you get
the buy signal, you put on a small
position because the volatility is too
high, but you start enjoying the ride
upward in the opposite direction. So
that's kind of the mentality. And if you
really build all that into your
strategies in the first place and you
understand why it does what it does,
then you start realizing I don't need to
worry about
the tail risk or the the risk of
something crazy happening. I've kind of
already built structure in there to make
those decisions. You know, like for
instance, a good example, uh we had I
think I've said this in other
interviews, we were working one night at
Trenstat. Uh we had a program. We
couldn't get our orders out that
afternoon. So I was staying with one of
the computer guys and we were under
pressure to get our orders in and uh we
couldn't find the bug and so I got to be
about 5:00. We were exhausted and uh I
said I'm going to go over and get some
Chinese food and you want something. And
we got that. We took a break had had
dinner. We got right back to it and
immediately found the problem. Just
being away and we couldn't see it
initially, but once we got back into it,
we found it right away. We fixed it.
Orders went in and at 8:00 at night, I
was about to go out out the door uh home
and I thought I'd check the quotes and
see what was going on. And our oil
position, which was long, was up $8 a
barrel from 32 to 40. And I'm thinking,
what the heck happened? And come to find
out that we had in uh invaded from Uwait
to protect U8. We it was the first Iraq
war. This was back during uh HW Bush's
uh presidency. And it was going well,
but war was breaking out in the Middle
East. So, you know, oil prices spiked. I
thought, "Wow, this is going to be
interesting because $8 a barrel of oil
oil on our long positions is going to be
a, you know, a pretty big profit for
tomorrow." I wake up in the morning and
I walk in and I said, "Trader, how how
are things going this morning?" He says,
"It's it's rough. Oil's at $22 a barrel.
The war is over and uh it went from $40
all the way down to 22. we get stopped
out and the risk and volatility on the
trade so great that unless you had about
a $20 million account, we couldn't even
short one contract of oil. So, it ended
up being
a situation where it's a once in a blue
moon type of thing. I think we lost uh I
forget it was like 6% that day or
something. It was a very big losing day
for Trendstat, but we were at new highs
in a couple months. But if you build
that into the strategies, then you know
what you have to do. It sort of adjusts
itself. It's not perfect, but you're
taking the stab in the right direction
and and I think that you have a plan in
place and you execute the plan.
>> That that's that's where being
systematic helps. One of the questions
which I had was in terms of uh today
when you look at the instruments that
that form a part of your trend following
system do you have indexes the broader
indexes like S&P 500 or NASDAQ or um or
it doesn't include that. So my question
was around indexes.
>> Yeah. What to give my equity exposure
anymore because of the both the tax laws
in the United States with marktomark uh
futures and straddles in the IRS code
combined together with the lack of wash
sale rules uh for securities. It's a lot
easier for me to trade futures to get my
stock exposure than to trade actual
stocks. So, I do I I could get back into
stocks in a second, but it it would
require for me in today's world to look
at a 50 stock portfolio probably and I'd
have to apply some automation to the
problem uh on the screening side. And
so, I may do that down the road if I'm
really bored, but um it doesn't make a
lot of sense. It's so much easier for me
to trade futures to get my stock
exposure.
>> Got it. And um as far as indexes are
concerned, have you again observed any
changes in terms of their structure? I
know you pointed out to the speed of
change um long I mean in 70s and 80s
versus way it is today. But then is
there anything else that you would want
to add in terms of how indexes have
changed?
>> Uh they seem to be dominated by
kind of like a few stocks. Uh the S&P is
capitalization weighted and
>> you know the magnificent seven and all
that. you know, they they get bigger and
bigger and become trillion dollar giants
and they dominate some of the indexes.
So, you're not getting the effect of one
stock necessarily, but you're getting
because of the high correlations
you get into the NASDAQ, you're getting
pretty much a tech stock index. But any
one company, you could have like a Tesla
be down 5% in the day and uh an Nvidia
up 10 and they offset each other to some
extent. So there's still a little bit of
extra protection there. So you don't
have to go out and buy 50 different
stocks individually and through all the
hassle of doing that, the commissions of
doing that, everything, uh tracking it,
uh it's it's easier for me to get the
exposure through an index futures.
Um let me extend that conversation to
this whole idea of active versus passive
which a lot of people talk about and
academia also says you know there's
there's very there's little that one can
do being active and hence it's better to
be passive and folks like it could be um
you know people like you or me I'm an
active um you know investor or trader we
we we obviously uh are active for a
reason. So, how do you kind of think
about passive investing
uh and uh all all that uh you know you
you know story about you can't beat the
index in the long run all of that how do
you look at that
>> I look at it is coming from a bunch of
people who don't know how to trade uh so
I take it with a grain of salt uh you
know I I think they don't understand the
psychological pressures like I do of not
only the traitor's own self and the uh
frustration, the anger, the um concern,
worry, uh greediness,
all those different emotions that you
can go through as a trader
that gets down to the client level. So,
if I'm managing, as I was back in this,
you know, 80s and 90s,
early 2000s, a bunch of client money,
I've got the clients putting the
pressure because they're they're going
all over the map emotionally. They're
calling me up trying to put
psychological pressure on me. So, I've
got to be even better because I've got
to not only deal with my own biases and
emotions, but I've got to deal with the
clients trying to exert even more
pressure on
>> situation.
And so, the academics who don't
understand trading just simply say,
well, the easy way to do this is just
ignore it. Yeah, but the clients won't
ignore it. So you buy and hold and the
returns over the long run are just fine.
But how about that draw down over there
in 197374?
How many of those clients stick around
for the 50% down move and then enjoy the
move that comes after to new highs? Not
many. And so there it doesn't take the
academic studies don't take into account
the psychology of the situation and the
reality that I see happens out in the
marketplace with clients and with
traders when you start factoring that
in. If I'm timing a mutual fund, let's
say,
uh, and I've got my beta against the
stock market of a essentially a stock
market portfolio, but I'm timing it. I
can get the beta down to like 0.5
and that is so much less risk than
taking on the buy and hold strategy. And
if I can get the returns anywhere close
to buy and hold, I would submit to you
it's a strategy that a client can live
with a lot better than they can the buy
and hold. M
>> but then there there's also this you
know trillions of money which is going
into passive is that also the reason why
you know dips get bought into and you
know it's it's essentially other than co
we we we've largely had an upward drift
so how do you see that which I don't
think that existed maybe in 70s or 80s
>> right and I'm not moving hundreds of
billions of dollars for myself uh in
retirement So yeah, if you're moving
billions, you have to start like if
you're the California pension plan or
something, you've got billions that you
have to figure out what to do with.
You're going to be a lot more passive
because you can't move that much money
into any one position very easily. It
takes sometimes days, weeks, and um
multiple managers. It's difficult. So
there you start getting more of the
academics saying, you know, just do the
passive thing. And in many cases, the
the academics are backing up the
government decision makers that would
require that the stuff be passive and
justifying it to protect their own jobs.
If we do have a down move, we could say,
"Well, we were passive. That's that's
what we're supposed to do. uh don't fire
me for losing 20% of the pension plan.
Uh but really in reality it's kind of
hard to do too much because you end up
just have so much money you can't you'd
move the market if you jumped in and
out. But that's one of the advantages
the small investor has and I would
include myself in that group small
investor
because I can go like when I was a CTA I
could uh look at the orange juice
market. it it trades maybe 200 300
contracts a day. I would not even
contemplate being in the orange juice
market when I've got 600 million I'm
trying to manage. But I can go in and
out with, you know, few contracts here
and there. It's no big deal. The market
doesn't care. So I have an advantage
over the big guys because I can dance in
and out anytime I want and the cost of
moving the market is very minimal. H but
you know since we're talking about
institutional versus retail trading and
the advantages each has I'm not sure if
you um you know there was this thing
which happened a few months back in
India where this firm uh American firm
Jane Street uh they uh they were accused
of market manipulation here in India.
Did you hear about that?
>> I didn't.
>> Okay. So the story is a bit like this.
So we have an index called Bank Nifty in
India and it's a weird index because
it's got very few stocks. So it's got
let's say 11 or 12 stocks. So because
it's an institution
they uh they could move the index and
that's what the regulator claims and
then they could the float is less than
those stocks and all of that and they
could move the index and then on the
other side you know they could make
money through options. What occurred to
me when you were telling me yeah retail
as as us as retail we have some
advantages but then institutions also
maybe have some advantages I don't know
so so so that's yeah that that's what uh
running on my mind
>> yeah they uh the institutional
advantages would be extreme
diversification
they can play in a lot of games at the
same time they have the computer
capability they have the speed of
execution in many case they're
vertically integrated so they can
actually do the execution themselves.
U the the smaller traders on the other
hand have the ability to move quickly
exploit a significant amount of uh of
the market for their own size and uh the
transaction costs that used to be very
large for the small trader have come
down to almost nothing. In some cases in
the US, you can trade stocks for zero
commissions. And futures contracts are
just very, very low cost. I used to pay
$100 round turns in futures and now it's
down in single digits. It's ridiculously
cheap. Everything's electronic
and uh you don't have to worry about out
trades as much and all the different
things you had to do in the old days.
So,
you know, there's advantages to wherever
you are, but I think what you have to do
as a trader, it would make sense to me,
is to analyze your own situation. You
don't want to trade like Tom Baso. You
want to trade like who you are. How how
many how many minutes a day are you
going to spend on trading? Are you going
to be glued to the screen or you going
to just run some orders at the end of
the day and update your stops? Uh what
markets are you going to participate in?
Are you going to trade futures? Are you
going to trade stocks? Are you going to
trade bonds? Are you going to trade
options?
Got to narrow it down. You can't do
everything
all the time. You know, it's you're a
human being. You got limitations. So,
you have to be focused. It's almost like
developing a business plan for your
trading and assessing here's the size of
dollars of capitalization that I've got.
Here's where my skills are. Here's what
I understand. Here's what I don't
understand.
uh here's the resources I have in terms
of uh friends or uh maybe relatives that
would like to do this with me and maybe
we have a joint project to get this
done. Uh where are we going with it and
set up a plan to get to where you want
to be?
>> Uh it's not just oh let's turn on the
screen and oh cocoa looks good today.
Let's go buy cocoa. You know that's
that's not a plan. That's just making it
up on the fly. It's
>> got it. you're going to end up just
along the way very frustrated.
>> So talking about uh you know I'm kind of
shifting gears. So something that you've
been doing for decades but then now with
technology and um you know AI it's
becoming easier. So just the way we were
talking about you know before we got
started. So in India at least a lot of
retail traders are automating their own
trades today. So there are the APIs of
different brokers are easily accessible
and of course the numbers in terms of
orderflow would be a small percentage
but then it's a growing uh cohort of
people who want to automate their own
trades and how do you look at it and
what has been your experience uh in
terms of automation?
>> My experience is that uh AI is changing
the way you code some fairly complex
things. uh the example we were talking
about before we came on uh where if I'm
sitting here working at my main screen
uh writing something for a Substack
piece or answering emails or uh
responding to people on uh x.com
I end up focusing most of my energy on
the screen that's right in front of me
that I'm talking to you on over here to
my left is another screen that's got my
trader platform And if I'm going to be
sitting here and I know I'm going to be
sitting here for 2 three hours, then
I'll go ahead and bring up my day
trading strategy. Well, the day trading
strategy is really simple, but it
requires my attention once every five
minutes. So I thought to myself, you
know, I'm going to as an experiment just
use u in that case it was Grock uh at
the time uh and ask Grock, could you do
a Pythonbased program that just reads my
clock on the computer? Every five
minutes is when the new bar is going to
show up over here on my left screen.
Give me a 15-second head start on that
and make an alarm go off. And so I'm
sitting here, you know, writing
something, answering an email, and all
of a sudden, ding, ding, ding. And so I
look over and I can move my stop if I
want, and I go right back to what I was
doing. And uh, it really slick. It took
me about three and a half hours to have
the AI go back and forth, and I'd say,
"Yeah, that's pretty good, but could we
do this instead or change the sound? I
want it a little bit more noticeable.
It's a little too quiet." And we played
with it a little bit. tried different
things, tried different durations of the
beeps and uh got it just exactly the way
I want it. Now it's an icon on my
desktop. I just hit trade timer and this
thing goes in the background and
automatic and then when I get out of it,
it stops. I could program in Python real
minimal stuff. Uh, I I programmed all my
life from university, but I have to say
to try to create what I created with AI
would have taken me probably days and I
did it in a couple hours.
So, it speeds up tremendously what
you're doing. You just have to get
better at describing to AI exactly what
you want because AI will assume things
if you don't tell it, you know, like
people assume. Yes.
>> Well, if you say something like, how
about generic? I'll give you a stupid
example. You say uh Grock or Claude AI
or any of these AIs, you say, "Okay, AI,
uh tell me the best way to produce the
biggest return possible of trading the
S&P 500 futures index over the last two
years. It will analyze the data and it
will come up with an answer for you. and
the answer will be an overoptimization
of the last two years and it'll probably
be garbage. So you have to be cognizant
of how specific you get. You want to
allow the flexibility for AI to really
solve your problem, but you don't want
to just have AI
go through the world of everything out
there and expect to get anything other
than an overoptimization of of history
of its knowledge base. And so you have
to use your brain a little bit with AI.
I think a lot of people are going to
misuse it and um they'll learn.
>> Yeah, that that's that's that's a part
of the game. So So but specifically
about um you know automation in the
context of trading to what extent is
your trading automated especially the
execution bit not the analysis but the
execution bit
>> execution is 100% automated.
You just switch it on
>> in
uh well it's yeah I just have to bring
it up and hit a couple buttons and off
it goes. So I I it automates the pull
down of the data. So it pulls down
prices first and gets them into storage
and then secondarily then I hit other
buttons and it executes the runs and I
hit other buttons and I transmit. So for
retail traders who want to automate your
I'm assuming you would suggest it's a
it's a better way to trade than do it
manually.
>> I would say for most people probably yes
but there are select people who I don't
know for example uh let's say you came
from a currency desk and you did nothing
but trade the Japanese yen for 10 years
on a currency desk. You're going to
you're going to be hardwired in your
brain to do different things with
trading. And it may be more appropriate
for you to I don't know deal with
the range trades, you know, buy and sell
and be a little quicker and glue to the
screen and use your contacts in the
industry to know which way to lean and I
don't know. Uh, everybody's different
there. There's not anybody that should
be doing exactly one thing. But there
are people that can do discretionary
trading better than I could. I I mean
what I did to get to where I am is to
analyze who I am. I'm I'm an engineer. I
know math. I know computers. I have X
amount of dollars that I'm managing. I
know futures. I know stocks. I've traded
bonds. I've traded some options. I've
traded foreign exchange. So I know this
these are my backgrounds. I know
computers. I know math. I have the
capabilities. So I put together my
strategies based on my situation. So
it's customdeveloped for me. It does not
apply to Joe Smith out there in the
world with $10,000 and he wants to trade
foreign exchange.
That's not going to work. You can't pick
up what I'm doing and translate it to
him because he's got a different
situation,
>> different problem to solve. I
>> I call it trading is nothing more than
solving your own financial problems and
uh my financial problems are different
than other people's.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. So uh so moving
on u Tom I had uh a a few couple of
questions and then we'll close the day.
So one is you've been uh known as
someone who is very serene in terms of
and keeping your calm in the markets and
you play two different roles. One you
were managing money at one point of time
and today you uh you manage your own
money. Now when I meet people who manage
others money you know you get two kinds
of responses. Some people say it's
easier to manage others money. I don't
get stressed when it's others money but
if it's my own money I get stressed. And
then there is another set of people who
say uh you know I cannot manage others
money. I'm okay managing uh my own
money. So how do you look at these two
um you know types of people in the
context of u being able to deal with the
stress or whatever anxiety that comes
with trading.
>> I I would back up from both examples and
say in life there are potential
stressors.
So, it could be something like
you pull up at a stoplight and the guy
in front of you is on his phone or
something. The light turns green and
he's sitting there holding up traffic
because he's not paying attention. That
could be a potential stressor. It only
becomes stress if you allow it to be
stress. But you would have to be aware
that it's affecting you that way and
just say to yourself, okay, you know,
the guy's on his phone. What an idiot.
But
this this sound I this music I've got
playing on the radio is really cool and
you just relax through it. And same
thing is true when somebody calls you as
a client and says, "How come you lost
money this last month?" You have to be
able to immediately your reaction is,
"Oh, that idiot. He doesn't know what
he's asking. The markets were down. Of
course we're down. That's stupid. Uh why
are you bothering me?" You know, that
could be a reaction. And it adds
potential stress to you. But it's only
stress if you take it that way. If you
then replace that with a mental
framework of, okay, he's a client. He's
paying me money to manage his money. He
has no idea what trading is all about.
That's why he hired me. And um I will
patiently answer his questions.
>> That that's
>> and then it doesn't become stress
anymore. So there's potential stressors
everywhere and what you said with both
examples is exactly true. But I think
that you just have to real you have to
be aware of yourself in your reaction to
those potential stressors and just uh be
able to change your mental uh process uh
towards those potential stressors and
they be they no longer become stress.
>> So Tom, can we say that your key message
is know thyself. So know yourself better
and the answers are all there.
>> Yeah, that would be a pretty good
summary. Stay in the now. Don't predict.
Just stay in the now and understand
yourself.
>> So uh so a couple of more things. Um you
know you you've been you you've been
watching markets for close to 50 years
and you've seen these cycles and
everything. What keeps you going even
today? Now you're still trading as we
speak.
>> So
>> yes,
>> what is it?
>> It is the um the brain tease of finding
the next trading strategy, the next
market to trade. Uh it's fun to be
creative. I think human beings,
the actions of human beings fall into
two major categories. One is the I do it
every day routinely. I brush my teeth. I
eat breakfast, I eat lunch, I uh you
know on I work out on Tuesdays and
Thursdays and Saturdays or whatever. You
know there's certain routines you get
into and those are very repetitive and
many cases when it comes to trading the
actual updating of your orders, the
sending of your orders, the transmitting
of that that becomes very routine. So
that's something that a computer can do.
What a computer cannot do, and you'll
fail if you ask AI to do it for you, I
believe, is to be creative and actually
examine markets and think, you know, I
should maybe create an option program
for the agricultural cont uh contracts
that could go into a drought or a heat
situation or a a pest uh situation where
corn goes from $2 to $4 or $4 to $8 and
uh the option would really really knock
it out of the park. I should examine
that. That'd be a good idea. So now
that's a human being coming up with a
creative idea that becomes the kernel of
maybe a future program, research
project, whatever, and you might end up
with another strategy in your uh your
portfolio.
>> That's the fun stuff.
>> So but then um we also social beings
Tom. So are there people who you speak
with about these trading ideas and you
know uh how how does that work?
>> Uh I usually get interviewed and I talk
to millions of people like
>> at least tens of thousands
>> u through various podcasts and
interviews and um exposts and uh
Substack articles that I write every now
and again. Um
yeah that's that's how I keep in touch
with a lot of people. One of the reasons
I called it enjoy the ride.world instead
of.com is not only was com taken at the
time butworld applies to my followers,
they're all around the world. So
>> yeah, indeed indeed.
>> So u you you spoke about options. So it
it kind of occurred to me. Have you
traded options? And you said you did a
bit. Uh what what's your view on options
as a product? um given your trading
style,
>> you know, it it can be very profitable
for somebody who wants to be more
manually involved. Uh I don't think
options lend themselves to the way I
like to trade, which is more automated.
Uh although I guess with robotics, you
probably could u create a bot that would
probably be able to deal with some of
that. Uh I just haven't it there's not a
lot of interest on my part of doing that
because it I think it's it's a lot more
involved to try to get um like a bot
working with respect to options and get
everything to flow perfectly. It'd be
quite the challenge. Uh so I tra I've
traded options mostly selling premium
and uh collecting it time decay stuff.
uh easy once a week decision making you
can do it manually doesn't lend itself
to automation very much
>> okay okay got it so yeah I think um
thank you uh Tom that brings us to the
end of this um longish maybe an hourong
conversation and um I I I I could I mean
one of the biggest things which I take
away from this conversation as you were
speaking was to maintain calm and to
reflect on what I'm thinking at any
given point of time and act based on
that reflection. So um thank you and u
wish you many more years of active
trading just the way you're doing and uh
uh if if it comes to if you if you come
to India at some point we would uh love
to host you and if I show up at uh in
that part of the world I would love to
see you. Oh
>> you're very welcome.
>> All right thank you and let's enjoy the
ride.
Perfect.